Boker tov בוקר טוב. Boker tov. What's up? Today's the last daf
דף, daf, Lamed Dalet ל"ד, Lamed Dalet, and we start with the
Mishnah משנה Mishnah on the bottom of Lamed Gimmel Amud Bet ל"ג
עמוד ב'. Lamed Gimmel Amud Bet. So we had been talking about
basic comparisons between Kodshei Mizbe'ach קדשי מזבח Kodshei Mizbe'ach and Kodshei Bedek
HaBayit קדשי בדק הבית, Kodshei Bedek HaBayit, and this last Mishnah משנה
Mishnah is also a type of a summary Mishnah משנה Mishnah but
not touches on Kedushah קדושה Kedushah issues but actually is quite broader.
So let's take a look. Ve-elu hen ha-nikbarim ואלו הן הנקברים. Ve-elu
hen ha-nikbarim. The following things you have to bury because of course
we've been talking about things that
are pasul פסול, pasul, you cannot redeem them. That was the end
of the last Mishnah משנה, Mishnah, which type of animals, Kodshim קדשים
Kodshim animals that died can be redeemed and cannot, and if they
can't be redeemed they have to bury. So based on that we
talk about a general category of things that have to be buried.
Kodshim she-hipilah קדשים שהפילה Kodshim she-hipilah or she-hipilu שהפילו, she-hipilu, if a
Korban קרבן Korban has a miscarriage. Now because then the animal it's
basically like a Korban קרבן Korban that died. Can't be redeemed, you
have to bury it. Now this assumes of course that the animal
that is born has the Kedushah קדושה Kedushah of a Korban קרבן,
Korban, which might be the question about whether a Korban קרבן, Korban,
a fetus is kadosh קדוש kadosh in the mother's womb or when
it's born. If it's only kadosh קדוש kadosh when it's born, then
this would not actually be considered a birth. So some want to
infer from this that this Mishnah משנה Mishnah is of the opinion
that the fetus is kadosh קדוש kadosh in the mother's womb, or
it could be a case that the person sanctified the animal when
it was already pregnant and therefore the fetus became directly kadosh קדוש.
kadosh. But this would essentially be a type of a case from
an instantiation of the case before, which it's a Korban קרבן Korban
that dies, it can't be redeemed, ein podein et ha-kodshim le-ha'achilam la-klavim
אין פודין את הקדשים להאכילם לכלבים, ein podein et ha-kodshim le-ha'achilam la-klavim,
or it can't be redeemed because it has to be alive to
be redeemed, and therefore you have to bury it. Okay, she-hipilu yikaveru
שהפילו יקברו. she-hipilu yikaveru. Hipilah shilya tikaver הפילה שליה תקבר, Hipilah shilya
tikaver,
similarly
if it's just not actually the fetus itself but just the placenta,
you have to bury it because you assume a placenta there is
a fetus there. Ve-shor ha-niskal ושור הנסקל, Ve-shor ha-niskal, so those are
very, that's like the transition from the previous Mishnah משנה, Mishnah, which
is a dead Korban קרבן. Korban.
Wait, so if it had given birth and you see the fetus
and then there's a placenta?
No, no, no, then you don't, right, right, right. This is only
because of a miscarriage issue. Okay, ve-shor ha-niskal ve-eglah arufah ושור הנסקל
ועגלה ערופה. ve-shor ha-niskal ve-eglah arufah. Now, now we talk about a
more general category of things that are asurim be-hana'ah אסורים בהנאה. asurim
be-hana'ah. Things that are forbidden in benefit, what are you supposed to
do with them? You can't leave them lying around, you might get
benefit from them. So therefore you have to get rid of them,
so you bury them. Now you might think maybe you should more
physically destroy them, we'll talk about that in a minute. But here
we're talking about burying them, so it is an ox that has
that you stoned because it killed somebody. Ve-eglah arufah ועגלה ערופה, Ve-eglah
arufah, when you broke the neck of the calf because you didn't
know who the murderer was. Ve-tzipporei metzora וצפורי מצורע, Ve-tzipporei metzora, the
birds of a metzora מצורע metzora that you know are used in
the ritual and you dip one in the blood and you send
free, anyway, and according to that, that is asur be-hana'ah אסור בהנאה.
asur be-hana'ah. But just the one you shot, right? Not the one
you sent? Well, the Gemara גמרא Gemara says true, the Gemara גמרא
Gemara says that the Torah תורה Torah would never say shillach le-takalah
שילח לתקלה, shillach le-takalah, right. Anyway, so those, but that asur be-hana'ah
אסור בהנאה. asur be-hana'ah. Ve-se'ar nazir ושער נזיר, Ve-se'ar nazir,
the hair of a nazir נזיר, nazir, which also is shaved in
the end of the process and is asur be-hana'ah אסור בהנאה. asur
be-hana'ah. U-peter chamor ופטר חמור, U-peter chamor,
now the firstborn donkey, you might remember, right, that we had a
whole discussion about that way back in Bechoros בכורות, Bechoros, whether the
firstborn donkey was asur be-hana'ah אסור בהנאה asur be-hana'ah or not. This
Mishnah משנה Mishnah is assuming that it is. There's a question about,
okay, so that's the firstborn donkey. U-basar be-chalav ובשר בחלב, U-basar be-chalav,
meat and milk, that's a classic case of issurei hana'ah איסורי הנאה.
issurei hana'ah. Ve-chullin she-nishchatu ba-azarah וחולין שנשחטו בעזרה. Ve-chullin she-nishchatu ba-azarah. Chullin
חולין chullin slaughtered in the Beis HaMikdash בית המקדש, Beis HaMikdash, that
also now, that really there's a whole discussion in the Gemara גמרא
Gemara whether chullin she-nishchatu ba-azarah וחולין שנשחטו בעזרה chullin she-nishchatu ba-azarah is
de-oraisa דאורייתא de-oraisa or not. Even if we say it's de-oraisa דאורייתא,
de-oraisa, that probably means de-oraisa דאורייתא de-oraisa in terms of the prohibition
to do it, not in terms of the object itself being forbidden.
So this is really the one case where it's most unclear why
the thing itself is forbidden. If you take a look at Rashi
רש"י, Rashi, Rashi רש"י Rashi says the following: Chullin she-nishchatu ba-azarah חולין
שנשחטו בעזרה Chullin she-nishchatu ba-azarah says Rashi רש"י, Rashi, mishum de-michlefi behu
kodshim she-ira behu pasul משום דמיחלפי בהו קדשים שאירע בהו פסול. mishum
de-michlefi behu kodshim she-ira behu pasul. Somebody sees something slaughtered in the
Beis HaMikdash בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash and they're not, it's not part
of the Korban קרבן, Korban, what do they assume it is? They
assume it's an invalid Korban קרבן. Korban. Well, the general halakhah הלכה
halakhah is that invalid Korbanot קרבנות, Korbanot, there's a general rule that
you burn them. So therefore they see this, you have to be
concerned that people are going to look at it as an invalid
Korban קרבן, Korban, and therefore you cannot go ahead and get hana'ah
הנאה hana'ah from it. Now the question is, why should it be
only buried? Well, that's the next opinion, I actually jumped ahead in
the Rashi רש"י. Rashi. The next opinion is Rabbi Shimon omer chullin
she-nishchatu ba-azarah yisarefu רבי שמעון אומר חולין שנשחטו בעזרה ישרפו. Rabbi Shimon
omer chullin she-nishchatu ba-azarah yisarefu. They have to be burned because they'll
be confused with invalid Korbanot קרבנות, Korbanot, right. So the first opinion
does not go that far, but the general question about the first
opinion is where does the issur hana'ah איסור הנאה issur hana'ah of
chullin she-nishchatu ba-azarah חולין שנשחטו בעזרה chullin she-nishchatu ba-azarah come from? Is
he assuming somehow that it's biblical? Is he assuming that it's rabbinic?
It's not at all clear. But the second opinion, there's a general
debate about what is the status of chullin she-nishchatu ba-azarah חולין שנשחטו
בעזרה chullin she-nishchatu ba-azarah as issurei hana'ah איסורי הנאה, issurei hana'ah, and
there might, and there is a... question whether that actually is a
biblical concern or not. All right, so that's that. Now the גמרא
Gemara goes on and it says like this: וכן חיה שנשחטה בעזרה.
ve-chen chayah she-nishchatah ba-azarah.
This opinion of רבי שמעון, Rabbi Shimon, now because he's concerned that
people will confuse it with פסולי קרבנות, psulei korbanot, you might say
that that's only if it looks like a כשר קרבן, kasher korban,
if it's a sheep or a cow or a goat. But he
goes so far to say no, even if you slaughtered a camel
in the עזרה, azarah, okay, or a pig in the עזרה, azarah,
or something like that, nevertheless there's a general rule that if you
slaughtered it in the עזרה azarah you treat it like a קרבן,
korban, and as we said, you treat it as a קרבן, korban,
a פסול קרבן, psul korban, even though it's not, it's חולין, chullin,
and and therefore we have the הלכה halachah that you burn it.
Yes.
So we burn it instead of burying these other previous cases. Yes.
How literal is that? Like so if I have בשר בחלב basar
be-chalav I can't throw it in the garbage? I have to bury
it?
So we'll take a look. I mean, basically it just means that
you don't have to burn it and the משנה Mishnah will say
you're not supposed to burn it, but but other forms of destruction
would be okay. So we'll see about that in a minute. We're
getting to that in the משנה. Mishnah. Okay? So let's keep on
going.
Okay. So the גמרא Gemara says like, where are we? Okay.
The משנה Mishnah also says נשרפין nisrafin and הנקברין. ha-nikbarin.
Right. So, right. ואלו הן הנשרפין, ve-elu hen ha-nisrafin, the following, that's
a
good point, I hadn't thought of that. The following are the things
that you have to burn. Now basically איסורי הנאה issurei hana'ah are
buried, but there are specific things that the תורה Torah says you
burn them. And what are the specific things that the תורה Torah
says burn them? Let's take a look. ואלו הן הנשרפין: ve-elu hen
ha-nisrafin: חמץ בפסח. chametz be-Pesach.
Now
that's actually a debate in פסחים Pesachim whether you burn it or
whether it's תשביתו בכל דבר tashbitu be-chol davar or only בשריפה, bi-sreifah,
whether you learn it out from נותר notar or not. So this
תנא tanna assumes that you do burn it. ישרף. yisaref. ותרומה טמאה,
u-trumah teme'ah, תרומה trumah that is טמאה, teme'ah, you cannot eat it,
but actually here the fact that you're allowed to burn it is
actually it's also a permission because you're allowed to benefit from it
as it is burning. So as it's, you know, the heat and
the light and so on. So this is one case where it's
not just that it's a חיוב chiyuv to burn it, but actually
there's a special allowance that as you're burning it you can benefit
from it. Question?
Yes. But can't a כהן kohen benefit from תרומה טמאה trumah teme'ah
like by feeding it to his animals?
No, it's like it's, you are allowed הנאת תרומה. hana'at trumah. On
one hand it's not technically איסורי הנאה issurei hana'ah like most things,
but there is a מצוה mitzvah to destroy it, so you're only
like allowed the הנאה hana'ah that comes as you're destroying it. Now
you could say why isn't feeding it to the animals destroying it?
But yeah, okay, but the גמרא Gemara does, but that's more of
an act of like considered an act of being נהנה. neheneh. So
it is true, it's not like classic איסורי הנאה. issurei hana'ah. Right,
because תרומה
טמאה trumah teme'ah right is is something that you're not, that it's
more like there's a מצוה mitzvah to be שורף soref and that
you can be נהנה neheneh as you're שורף. soref.
So feeding it to your animals is not like you're over on
being, on the איסור הנאה issur hana'ah by תרומה טמאה, trumah teme'ah,
it's more like you're over on the חיוב chiyuv of how you're
supposed to destroy it. But you're right, it is an unusual category.
Okay. וערלה וכלאי הכרם. ve-orlah ve-khil'ei ha-kerem. ערלה וכלאי הכרם, orlah ve-khil'ei
ha-kerem, now where do you get from there you're supposed to burn
it? So from כלאי הכרם khil'ei ha-kerem the גמרא Gemara makes a
דרשה drashah פן תקדש המלאה הזרע אשר תזרע, pen tikdash ha-mele'ah ha-zera
asher tizra, lest it becomes holy, and the דרשה drashah is תקדש
תוקד אש, tikdash tukad esh, that it has to be burnt. How
do you learn from ערלה? orlah? So רש"י Rashi says ערלה orlah
is connected to כלאים. kil'ayim. But actually the גמרא Gemara never, there's
פסוקים psukim that I forget, רש"י Rashi doesn't quote, but there are
sometimes the גמרא Gemara makes פסוקים psukim that make the דרשה. drashah.
One minute. וערלה וכלאים גמרי מהדדי. ve-orlah ve-khil'ayim gamri me-hadadi.
Or isn't the פסוק לא תזרע כרמך כלאים? lo tizra karmekha khil'ayim?
No, כלאים, kil'ayim,
yeah, but I forget. Anyway, there are גמרות Gemarot that connect it,
but not specifically for this. רש"י Rashi assumes that they're connected for
this. What?
They come together all the time in questions.
Yeah, but that's in terms of the question of whether it applies
in חוץ לארץ. chutz la-aretz. Okay. Okay,
where are we? Okay. את שדרכן לישרף ישרף את שדרכן לקבר יקבר.
et she-darkan li-saref yisaref et she-darkan le-kaver yikaver. Things that are normally
burnt should be burnt, things that are normally buried should be buried.
What does that mean? We just got through saying it should be
burnt. So it means that things that are liquid, you don't normally,
you can't burn liquid. So what do you do if you have
a liquid of תרומה trumah or liquids of כלאים kil'ayim or of
ערלה? orlah? So those you can't burn, so you would bury. Well
if it's oil... Well if it's oil you could burn it, but
if it's other liquids that are not oil, so what are you
supposed to do with it? Let's say it's wine.
So we don't make a מדורה? medurah? Well right. So you burn
liquids if it's flammable?
No, I mean how would you burn wine? I mean you'd have
to,
I mean if it is
oil you do burn it, okay. Liquids that are not normally burnt,
you don't burn, you bury them. Now actually going back to Charlie's
point, the הלכה halachah of תרומה טמאה trumah teme'ah is that you,
is that you don't, if you have wine you don't burn it.
What you do or you don't bury it, what you do is
you sort of sprinkle it and it serves as like an air
freshener. That's like another example of like getting some indirect benefit as
you are, you know, doing something to destroy it. So why feeding
it to your animals isn't included in that category is an interesting
question. I mean if you can burn it as oil and if
you can use it as air freshener,
yeah, I'd have to get back to you on that. But it's
a good question. But that is what the גמרא Gemara says actually
you do about wine of תרומה טמאה. trumah teme'ah. But other things
that you can't burn that are liquid you would bury.
ומדליקין
בפת בשמן של תרומה. Umadlikin b'pas b'shemen shel terumah. So this actually
is exactly qualifying that, which is saying yeah, there are some things
that you actually will burn, some things like oil. So oil or
bread of תרומה טמאה Terumah Tmeiah you will actually use as you
would actually use as fuel. It's a question why he has to
repeat the case of פת, pas, not exactly clear. Okay, so now
we, so that's so far the basic rule. The basic rule is
that you, things that are אסור בהנאה assur b'hana'ah you bury. Specific
things the תורה Torah tells you you burn. תרומה טמאה Terumah Tmeiah
is an interesting category because it's not אסור בהנאה, assur b'hana'ah, but
there still is a מצוה mitzvah to destroy it and to burn
it, and you can be נהנה neheneh from it as it is
being, as it is being destroyed. Okay, so now it goes on.
כל הקדשים שנשחטו חוץ מזמנם וחוץ ממקומם הרי אלו ישרפו. Kol hakodashim
shenishchatu chutz mizmanam v'chutz mimkomam harei elu yisarefu. Now we get to
the rule that was somewhat implicit in the earlier discussion about חולין
שנשחטו בעזרה, chullin shenishchatu b'azarah, that if there's a פסול psul by
קרבנות, korbanot, they have to be burned. The תורה Torah is explicit
about this by נותר. notar. It
says והנותר באש ישרפו, v'hanotar ba'esh yisarefu, and the גמרא Gemara in
פסחים Pesachim says that כל דבר שפסולו בהקדש נשרף. kol davar shepsulo
b'hekdesh nisraf. Anything that's a פסול קרבן psul korban is burnt. So
חוץ מזמנו וחוץ ממקומו chutz mizmano v'chutz mimkomo does not mean שחוטי
חוץ, shchutei chutz, by the way. It means that it means that
they were what was חוץ מזמנו? chutz mizmano? It means that they
were slaughtered with the דעת da'as to eat them חוץ מזמנו וחוץ
ממקומו, chutz mizmano v'chutz mimkomo, so we're getting back to פיגול pigul
types of concerns. Okay, now, so basically that would include really any
type of a thing that is a פסול הקדש psul hekdesh is
burned. Now, the top of ל"ד עמוד א'. lamed daled amud aleph.
אשם תלוי ישרף. Asham talui yisaref. This is a more interesting case
because this is an אשם תלוי asham talui you burn. Now, what
do you mean you burn? The תורה Torah says that if you
bring an אשם, asham, you know, you eat the meat, it's like
a חטאת chatas or the כהנים kohanim eat the meat. But the
אשם תלוי asham talui is a specific אשם asham that is brought
because you're not sure if you sinned. You might have done a
sin that's חייב חטאת. chayav chatas. I might have eaten that forbidden
חלב, chelev, but I don't know. And there's a reason, grounds to
think that I have. Exactly what that category is we will see,
that's all the next מסכת. masechet. But if there's sufficient grounds to
think I have, but I'm not certain, I bring an אשם תלוי.
asham talui. The purpose of an אשם תלוי asham talui is to
protect me, as it were, to atone for me in the interim
unless, until I find out whether I have or have not sinned.
Now, let's say I went and I brought this אשם תלוי, asham
talui, and before I had a chance to eat the meat, or
the כהנים kohanim had a chance to eat the meat, I realized
I hadn't sinned. So the whole thing was for no purpose. There's
no sin that it was corresponding to. Now, why don't we say
nevertheless it was brought on the possibility? But no, now we know
there is no sin that it was corresponded to. If I know
I did sin, then at least it was good, it helped for
that sin in the interim. But now there is no sin that
it was needed for. ישחט ויקבר. Yishachet v'yikaver. If I didn't sin,
if you did sin, then you are, right, correct. So now what
do I do? So now retroactively this is חולין, chullin, חולין שנשחטו
בעזרה. chullin shenishchatu b'azarah. Okay, so what do you do with it?
Now, you could have said that goes back to the old debate
of חולין שנשחטו בעזרה, chullin shenishchatu b'azarah, but this is a little
different because this at the time you slaughtered it, it had the
קדושה kedusha of a קרבן. korban. You only sort of realized retroactively
that it wasn't necessary. So let's take a look. So the הלכה
halacha here is ישרף. yisaref. There the more תנא קמא Tanna Kamma
agrees that you burn it. That really does look like a קרבן
korban that became פסול pasul and it was after it was slaughtered,
okay? And that's not a straight חולין שנשחטו בעזרה. chullin shenishchatu b'azarah.
And therefore, therefore even the תנא קמא Tanna Kamma here says that
you burn it because it really looks, it's much closer to the
category of a קרבן korban that became פסול. pasul. Nevertheless, רבי יהודה
Rabbi Yehuda still says, no, רבי יהודה אומר יקבר. Rabbi Yehuda omer
yikaver. No, in the end it's חולין, chullin, it's not קדשים, kodashim,
and therefore it's buried, it is not burned. Now, חטאת העוף הבאה
על הספק. Chatas ha'of haba'ah al hasafek. What about a bird חטאת
chatas that would come for a ספק? safek? What would be this
be? So this would be a case that there would be with,
if a woman has to bring a קרבן korban if she gives,
if she has a, you know, after childbirth to allow her to
enter the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash and eat בקדשים. b'kodashim. And that
קרבן, korban, now let's say she's not certain if it was a
viable child. She had a miscarriage, not certain if it's a type
of a child that you're חייב chayav to bring a קרבן korban
or not. What should she do? Not bring a קרבן, korban, then
she's never going to be able to enter the בית המקדש. Beis
Hamikdash. Bring a קרבן, korban, but then maybe it's, you're not obligated
to bring it and then it's חולין בעזרה. chullin b'azarah. So the
גמרא Gemara learns out really from a פסוק pasuk that you're allowed
in that case to bring a קרבן korban on a ספק. safek.
So you bring this bird קרבן, korban, the חטאת העוף על הספק.
chatas ha'of al hasafek. Now, the only thing is is that as
we know, what do you do with a bird sacrifice? You do
מליקה, melikah, right? So if it turns out that it's not really
obligated, although she's on the one hand allowed to bring it, if
she's not really obligated, then it's a נבילה. neveilah. You can't eat
it. So what are you supposed to do with it? You've got
to destroy it. Now, the reason you probably need a פסוק pasuk
to tell you you can bring the קרבן korban to begin with
is because of what is because you know otherwise it would be
חולין בעזרה chullin b'azarah type of a concern.
Of course, maybe so there is a ראשון, Rishon, trying to remember
who said, that it's not such a חולין בעזרה chullin b'azarah concern
because in the end what's unique about a חטאת העוף chatas ha'of
is that you actually just, you know, sprinkle the blood on the
מזבח, mizbeach, it doesn't really get burned or whatever, and therefore it's
not so much like you're actually burning stuff on the מזבח. mizbeach.
רבי עקיבא איגר Rabbi Akiva Eiger does not like that
idea. But maybe given the fact that there is a need to
bring such a קרבן, korban, we can say, alright, it's not so
bad if you're not actually putting it on the מזבח mizbeach itself.
Anyway, the גמרא Gemara actually, not this גמרא Gemara but another גמרא
Gemara learned it from a פסוק pasuk that you're not, you're not
concerned about that, that you're allowed to bring it, you don't worry
about חולין בעזרה, chullin ba-azarah, but at the end of the day,
this might be a נבילה. neveilah. So what do you do with
this חטאת העוף? chatas ha-of? So the משנה Mishnah says, תשרף, tisaref,
again, burn it. It looks like a קרבן korban that's פסול, pasul,
so therefore if it looks like a קרבן korban that's פסול, pasul,
burn it. רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda אומר, omer, יטילנה לאמה. yatilena la-amah.
No, you throw it into the אמה. amah. The אמה amah was
sort of like a, you know, like in Israel they've got, you
know, when you squeegee everything into the middle of the floor and
then it runs out. So they had something like that in the
בית המקדש. Beis HaMikdash. They had like an open sewer, almost, it
sounds bad, whatever, an open type of a thing where there was
run, canal, there was running water and all the blood would wash
into that and it would wash out. So he says it's a
bird, apparently a bird will dissolve pretty easily, so you don't have
to bother burning it, you just throw it in that canal. Is
it a type of קבורה? kevurah? Well, I think that's a type
of a קבורה. kevurah.
Why didn't he say just two lines above, he said קבורה? kevurah?
Yeah, it's a good question and you know, the גמרא Gemara does
not really explore this. Well, no, but because an אשם תלוי asham
talui is a big, you know, is a big animal. You can't
just throw it into the sewer, it'll get, it'll get stuck. Here
the idea is that it'll dissolve and it's not a problem. So
it's a variation of the קבורה kevurah that's easier. You're right there
in the בית המקדש, Beis HaMikdash, just throw it there. Presumably, presumably.
Maybe he also feels that this a little bit more looks like
you're treating it as קדשים, kodshim, so maybe it's a little bit
better, but yeah, it's not clear.
יטילנה לאמה. yatilena la-amah. כל הנקברים לא ישרפו. kol ha-nikbarim lo yisarefu.
Now here becomes the כלל. klal. Anything that has to be buried,
don't burn it. וכל הנשרפין לא יקברו. ve-kol ha-nisrafin lo yikaveru. Anything
that has to be burned, don't bury. Now why? So let's deal
with each one of these separately. Why can you not burn something
that needs to be buried? I mean, what's the problem? You're totally
destroying it. So we will see, the גמרא Gemara will basically say
because there's a הלכה halacha that if something has to be burned,
after you burn it and you turn it into ashes, you're allowed
to derive הנאה. hana'ah. It's not true about something that needs to
be buried. Something that needs to be buried is never permissible even
after you burn it. We'll talk about why in the גמרא. Gemara.
So therefore, if I were to burn something that needs to be
buried, I would say, oh look, it's burned, it's got to be
okay, I will treat it like the things that have to be
burned and I will derive benefit, and actually if there's no מצוה
mitzvah to burn it, it is always forbidden in benefit. So don't
burn it. Now can you destroy it in other ways? Yeah, why
not? You know, go ahead. The idea is that it should not
be a source of sinning, so go ahead and you know, flush
it down the toilet or you know, put it in your trash
incinerator, any type of destruction that it will not lead to a
possibility that somebody might indirectly benefit from it, right? If it's a
type of a destruction that you might indirectly benefit, then that would
not be advisable. But the key is don't burn it because then
you'll come to give it the leniencies of things that need to
be burned. One, one minute. Why can you not bury things that
need to be burned? Well, that's more obvious because if it's a
מצוה mitzvah to burn it, it's a מצוה mitzvah to burn it.
You can't bury it. You have a מצוה mitzvah to burn it.
Okay, that's the most obvious reason. For some reason רש״י Rashi doesn't
say that. רש״י Rashi says why? דילמא אתי איניש ואשכחיה ואכליה. dilma
ati inish ve-ashchechei ve-achlei.
That if you're supposed to burn it and you bury it, maybe
accidentally it won't be as fully destroyed, right? It's more fully destroyed
when it's burned. So maybe someone will in, will
improperly benefit from it. Okay, which is a little bit of, which
is strange because on the one hand just say because there's a
מצוה mitzvah to burn it, why do you need that? It's a
very secondary reason. And also if you're concerned that people, it won't
be destroyed well enough, why are you not concerned about it in
the case of נקברים? nikbarim? So you know, that is a quite
strange רש״י Rashi that the אחרונים acharonim are really challenged with. But
the basic, the simple reason is, well it depends, there's a מחלוקת
machlokes how we פסקן pasken about חמץ. chametz. But the simple thing
is that if it's a מצוה mitzvah to burn it, you got
to burn it because that's the מצוה. mitzvah. If it's a מצוה
mitzvah to bury, you can really destroy it anyway, but don't burn
it because then you'll come to give it the leniencies of things
where there is a מצוה mitzvah to burn. Yes, Charlie, you had
a question. Okay.
So רבי יהודה אומר אם רצה להחמיר על עצמו לשרוף את הנקבר
רשאי. Rabbi Yehuda omer im ratza le-hachmir al atzmo lisrof es ha-nikbar
rashai. If he wants to be more strict and do a more
full destruction like burn it, you're allowed. That'll more total get it
out of the world. We're not going to be concerned that in,
that people might benefit from it afterwards. אמרו לו, amru lo, they
said to him, אין מותר לשנות. ein mutar leshanos. No, no fooling
around. You got to keep things in their clear category. It could
also just be a basic point that you know, that if you
don't, if you fudge the line in one category, you come to
fudge the line in the other category. Let's just keep every category
distinct and therefore we won't come to inadvertently do one rather than
the other. Okay, so now let's take a look. So that is
a quite heavy משנה, Mishnah, right? Gets us into a whole new
category of things of איסורי הנאה issurei hana'ah and how do you
destroy them? There are other par, there are other somewhat parallels to
this משנה, Mishnah, like there's a whole משנה Mishnah in קידושין Kiddushin
about a man who tries to marry a woman with these types
of objects, right? And then the question is are you considered to
own איסורי הנאה? issurei hana'ah? Do they, are they considered to have
value? But this is the one of the few places that there's
this sort of collection of the list of איסורי הנאה issurei hana'ah
and the different הלכות, halachos, here the basic difference about whether they
are burned or buried. So let's take a look at the
גמרא. Gemara. So the משנה Mishna says you have to bury the
hair of a נזיר. Nazir. רמי ליה
טבי לרב נחמן. Rami lei Tavi le-Rav Nachman. So רמי, Rami, so
טבי Tavi showed, excuse me, לרב נחמן, le-Rav Nachman,
raised a problem, a contradiction. תנן, Tnan, שיער נזיר יקבר. se'ar Nazir
yikaber. Our משנה Mishna says you have to bury it. רמינהי, Reminehi,
I'll ask you, we have a משנה Mishna in עבודה זרה. Avodah
Zarah. It says האורג מלא הסיט מצמר בכור בבגד ידלק הבגד. ha-oreg
melo hasit mi-tzemer bechor be-veged yidaleik ha-veged. Let's say you sowed into
a... from the sheep of a בכור, bechor, from the wool of
a בכור, bechor, right? And it's a בכור bechor that's... it's אסור
בהנאה, assur be-hana'ah, it's קדשים. kodshim. All קדשים kodshim is אסור בהנאה
assur be-hana'ah until you שחט shecht it and eat it and so
on. So let's say you sheared the wool of a בכור, bechor,
which you weren't allowed to do, and you sowed from it a
מלא הסיט. melo hasit. מלא הסיט Melo hasit is basically
the length from the tip of your thumb to the tip of
your pinky. Okay, oh not your pinky, excuse me, the tip of
your forefinger, right? That's a מלא הסיט, melo hasit, this length from
the tip of your thumb to your forefinger. So you did that
much of a wool of a בכור bechor and you wove it
into a בגד, beged, to a garment. ידלק הבגד, Yidaleik ha-beged, you
have to burn it. Okay, now that's fine, that's קדשים. kodshim. קדשים,
Kodshim, what do you do if there's a problem with it? You
burn it.
משיער הנזיר ופטר חמור, Mi-se'ar ha-Nazir u-feter chamor, let's say you used
the hair of a נזיר Nazir or the hair of a donkey,
of a donkey that was a firstborn, that's also אסור בהנאה. assur
be-hana'ah. בשק, Be-sak, and you wove it into a שק. sak. The
reason it says שק sak as opposed to a garment is because
they would use hair for sackcloths and they would use wool for
garments, but really it is immaterial. Okay, so you wove this forbidden
hair into a שק, sak, ידלק השק, yidaleik ha-sak, you have to
burn it. So you see you burn it, it's not just that
you bury it. Why did it say burn, why did it say
bury? אמר ליה, Amar lei, he said back to him,
כאן בנזיר טמא כאן בנזיר טהור. kan be-Nazir tamei kan be-Nazir tahor.
It's different whether the נזיר Nazir is טמא tamei or טהור. tahor.
Why is it the difference? Because the תורה Torah actually says what
do you do with the hair of a נזיר. Nazir. So the
תורה Torah says that when the נזיר Nazir is טהור tahor and
he finished his נזירות, nezirus, then he shaves his hair and you
burn the hair under the meat of the קרבן korban that you're
cooking, whatever, it's part of the ritual of what you... of the
burning of the hair of a נזיר טהור. Nazir tahor. So therefore
he says, ah, that does have a מצות שריפה. mitzvas sreifah. Now
of course that's a little bizarre because it has a מצות שריפה
mitzvas sreifah when you're doing the ritual in the בית המקדש. Beis
HaMikdash. Right, here you have apparently the hair was used outside of
the בית המקדש. Beis HaMikdash. So presumably the גמרא Gemara understands here,
and this is what a point that רב וולוול Rav Velvel makes,
the גרי"ז Griz makes, he says that the idea that you burn
the hair of a נזיר טהור Nazir tahor is not just part
of the מצוה mitzvah of the ritual of what you do with
the נזיר, Nazir, but it's also part of the דין din of
the actual object of the hair itself. The תורה Torah says that
the hair is obligated in שריפה. sreifah. So even if somehow it
wasn't used in the ritual, if it's outside of the בית המקדש,
Beis HaMikdash, it has to be burned. So when it's a נזיר
טהור, Nazir tahor, there's a מצוה mitzvah to burn it. That's where
we say burn it. When it was a נזיר טמא, Nazir tamei,
the תורה Torah never had it as part of a ritual of
שריפה. sreifah. So therefore, although he shaves his hair, you don't burn
it, and therefore that was when we would say to bury it.
Okay,
so that was his answer.
אמר ליה, Amar lei, שנית נזיר אנזיר. shanita Nazir a-Nazir. Fine, you
answered the נזיר Nazir question. That was a nice distinction. פטר חמור
אפטר חמור קשיא. Peter chamor a-peter chamor kashya. What about פטר חמור?
peter chamor? Our משנה Mishna says what do you do with it?
You bury it. There's no מצות שריפה mitzvas sreifah by פטר חמור,
peter chamor, it's just אסור בהנאה, assur be-hana'ah, right? That if you
refuse, you know, you refuse to redeem the פטר חמור peter chamor
with a sheep, it becomes אסור בהנאה. assur be-hana'ah. There's a question
is it אסור בהנאה assur be-hana'ah beforehand, whatever, anyway we learned that
in בכורות. Bechoros. But it's אסור בהנאה, assur be-hana'ah, there's no מצות
שריפה. mitzvas sreifah. So how come here it says burn? You didn't
have... you don't have an answer to that. The נזיר Nazir was
a nice distinction. אישתיק ולא אמר ליה ולא מידי. Ishtik ve-lo amar
lei velo midei. He was silent, he didn't have anything to respond
to him. אמר ליה, Amar lei, מידי שמיע לך? midi shmi'a lach?
So then רב נחמן Rav Nachman said back to טבי, Tavi, he
said, have you heard an answer about this? You're asking such a
good question, maybe you have an answer. והא, Ve-ha, אמר ליה, amar
lei, הכי אמר רב ששת. hachi amar Rav Sheshes. Yeah, actually רב
ששת Rav Sheshes gave me an answer, which is interesting why רב
ששת Rav Sheshes and רב נחמן Rav Nachman were sort of colleagues,
so presumably he might have raised this issue with רב ששת. Rav
Sheshes. Ah, here's what רב ששת Rav Sheshes says. הכי אמר לי
רב ששת, Hachi amar li Rav Sheshes, כאן בשק כאן בשיער. kan
be-sak kan be-se'ar. Ah, it matters whether you're dealing with just the
hair or with a שק. sak. If it's just the hair and
you bury the hair, so what's going to happen if somebody happens
to... it gets uncovered and somebody gets... comes across the hair? They'll
maybe assume why was this hair buried, maybe it was איסור הנאה,
issur hana'ah, what's the likelihood they're going to use it anyway? But
let's say you bury a שק sak and then the שק sak
gets uncovered. Oh, so you're going to use it, it's a good
שק. sak. So when it's actually now in a usable condition, it's
woven into a שק, sak, then we have to be extra careful
and destroy it. Now of course it's interesting, we don't say destroy
it in other ways, right? We're not concerned about this rule don't
burn things that have to be buried. Because at the end of
the day, burning something was the best way of physically destroying it.
I mean you could say put it in a trash compactor, you
could say, you know, the גמרא Gemara says, you know, other ways
of trying to physically destroy it, but burning is always a pretty
good way of destroying something. So here where we are concerned that
burial won't be enough, we say forget about the limits of not
burning, just go ahead and burn it.
There've been a whole number of times where they say
יוליכו לים המלח, yolicho le-Yam HaMelach, you don't have that...
I
understand, well first of all יוליכו לים המלח... yolicho le-Yam HaMelach... But
often the ים המלח Yam Hamelach things are like metal and whatever
which really would sink and dissolve. Right. I understand. There are alternatives,
but clearly burning is going to be the best way of actually
destroying it. Since we're actually talking about a חמץ בפסח Chametz b'Pesach
story and about burning it, I'm always reminded of this story that
I remember that Rav Aharon Lichtenstein said that when he was once
with Rav Soloveitchik on פסח Pesach and they were driving in the
car, it was חול המועד Chol HaMoed whatever, and he opened up
the glove compartment and there was a Devil Dog. Now you have
to realize this was before Hostess and all those things were accepted
as kosher, so that which anyway, whatever, it was a Devil Dog.
So he said to the רב, Rav, he says, what do we
do? Rav Soloveitchik says, burn it! He says, we can't burn it,
we sold it! It's not ours! You should just burn it!
So
then after the שיעור, shiur, all of the Israelis were saying, what's
a Devil Dog? And all of the Americans were saying, I didn't
know Devil Dogs were kosher!
Anyway, so okay, so just burn it. That's the answer, just burn
it. Okay, so that's what he says. איתמר נמי, Itmar Nami, it
was said similarly, אמר רבי יוסי ברבי חנינא, Amar Rabbi Yose b'Rabbi
Chanina, כאן בשק כאן בשיער. kan b'sak kan b'se'ar. If it's just,
if it's a sackcloth, then you've just got to burn it, even
though you're not supposed to burn those types of things, but if
it's a sack, people might actually find it and use it, so
burn it. If it's hair, then you can bury it. רבי אליעזר
אומר, Rabbi Eliezer omer, so that seemed to be a pretty good
answer. Rabbi Eliezer says, כאן בנזיר טהור וכאן בנזיר טמא. kan b'nazir
tahor v'kan b'nazir tamei. So he went back to the old answer,
which ignored the issue about the פטר חמור peter chamor and he
focused on the נזיר, nazir, and he said if it's a נזיר
טהור, nazir tahor, the hair has to be burned, if it's a
נזיר טמא, nazir tamei, it's just buried. אמר ליה, Amar lei, now
we have another question.
ליבטל שק ברובא, Libatel sak b'rubba, or not really שק sak but
the שיער ברובא. se'ar b'rubba. Why isn't the hair בטל ברוב? batel
b'rov? Okay, which is,
which you know, which is you have a little hair that gets
mixed up in all of the other material, in all of the
other hair, so why don't we just say בטל ברוב batel b'rov
and therefore it gets woven in and forget about the whole thing?
The question is why is the hair, assuming you got the hair
of the נזיר, nazir, it was one, it says one strand was
woven in. So you have one strand of the hair mixed up
with all the other hair that you're using or one strand of
wool mixed up with all the other wool, why don't we just
say בטל ברוב? batel b'rov? It should be ליבטל שיער ברובא. libatel
se'ar b'rubba. Yeah, I know, so that's why the גר"א Gra tries
to take out the words ליבטל שק, libatel sak, he just says
ליבטל ברובא. libatel b'rubba. The word שק sak really doesn't fit. Okay,
anyway. So אמר רב פפא, Amar Rav Pappa, בציפורתא. b'tzipporta. No, what
it is is that you made like a little bird design on
it. Why of all things mention a bird? Not clear, but the
point is it's not בטל batel because it's ניכר nikkar exactly where
it is. You wove this string into a design, so it's not
that you could say you don't know where that particular string is.
So the גמרא Gemara says fine, if you know where it is,
ציפורתא לשלפינהו. tzipporta lishlefinu. So then just remove that design. If you
know exactly where it is, remove that and burn that, who has
to destroy the whole thing? אמר רבי ירמיה, Amar Rabbi Yirmiya, הני
רבי יהודה היא, hani Rabbi Yehuda hi, דאמר אם רצה להחמיר עצמו
לשרוף את הנקברין רשאי. d'amar im ratza l'hachmir atzmo lisrof es hanikbarin
rashai. This is Rabbi Yehuda that says you can be מחמיר, machmir,
you can burn things that have to be buried. Okay, what does
that have to do with the answer about, that's just the form
of destroying, that still doesn't answer why destroy the whole thing? Well
maybe the גמרא Gemara seems, well if he's allowed you to be
מחמיר machmir one way, he'll also tell you to be מחמיר machmir
another, but why should it require you to be מחמיר? machmir? It
doesn't really clearly how it answers that, which is sort of what
the גמרא Gemara responds. אמר ליה, Amar lei, קקשין לשלפינהו, k'kashyan lishlefinu,
we were asking cut that section out, ואת מוקמת לה כרבי יהודה?
v'at mokmas lei k'Rabbi Yehuda? And you're telling me oh it's Rabbi
Yehuda you can burn it. It's an irrelevant point. We just want
to say cut out that section, don't destroy the whole thing. So
אמר ליה, Amar lei, הכי קאמר.
hachi
k'amar. No, no, this is what I mean. אם אפשר לשלפינהו מותר.
Im efshar lishlefinu mutar. If you can cut it out, good. If
for some reason you can't cut it out, not that clear why
you couldn't cut it out, but if for some reason that's not
an option, ואם לאו, v'im lav, then you go ahead and destroy
it. Now as to the question, going back to the earlier question,
why did it say burn rather than bury? Remember, that was our
earlier question, right? The hair of a נזיר nazir and a פטר
חמור peter chamor you're supposed to bury and here it says burn.
So we so far have two answers. One, if it's a שק,
sak, there's a greater concern of people misuse, of you know, people
misusing it and therefore we say burn it. Or by a נזיר
nazir at least we gave the answer that it was a נזיר
טהור, nazir tahor, but our outstanding question, our bigger question was why
burn rather than bury? So going back to that question, אוקמה כרבי
יהודה, ukma k'Rabbi Yehuda, say it goes like Rabbi Yehuda, דאמר אם
רצה להחמיר עצמו לשרוף את הנקברין רשאי. d'amar im ratza l'hachmir atzmo
lisrof es hanikbarin rashai. When it says burn it, it doesn't mean
you have to burn it, it means just burn it. It means
that that's always an option, so it said burn it but it
was not mean that it was necessary. That was Rabbi Yehuda that
in general allows you to burn. So what we now have three
answers why it said burn this hair that was woven in. One
is that you're not required to but it's Rabbi Yehuda who allows
you to burn it. One is what seems to be the best
answer for both cases is that it's a שק sak and if
it's a שק... sak... meaning if it's something that if we're concerned
that if it's buried it will be found and will be misused,
and there's a big difference if it's a sack or if it's
just hair, so there we're going to say you must burn it.
And the other answer didn't really address the פטר חמור Peter Chamor
case but said by נזיר Nazir there's a difference between hair of
נזיר טהור, Nazir Tahor, hair of נזיר טמא. Nazir Tamei. Okay, so
that was working out the hair of נזיר Nazir and the פטר
חמור. Peter Chamor. Now we get to the נשרפין. Nisrafin. ואלו הן
הנשרפין. Ve'elu Hen HaNisrafin. אמר מר, Amar Mar, חמץ בפסח ישרף. Chametz
BePesach Yisaref.
So one of the first cases there was חמץ Chametz coming up.
סתם מתניתין כרבי יהודה. Stam Matnitin KeRebi Yehuda. That's like רבי יהודה
Rebi Yehuda that אמר אין ביעור חמץ אלא שריפה. Amar Ein Biur
Chametz Ela Sreifa. רבי יהודה Rebi Yehuda learns it out from נותר
Notar that you have to burn it. There's a question how we
פסקן, Pasken, and at least this משנה Mishna is פסקן-ing Pasken-ing that
it has to be burned. תרומה טמאה וערלה. Truma Tmeia VeOrla.
Now the other cases that you burn is תרומה טמאה Truma Tmeia
and ערלה. Orla.
A little bit funny though because רבי יהודה Rebi Yehuda appears in
a
whole bunch later in the משנה Mishna and that's what the גמרא
Gemara is going to ask why he isn't mentioned earlier.
Right, although you know could be שיטתיה סבירא ליה Shitatei Savira Lei
by that, but it's a good point. Okay, it doesn't say
he... now תרומה טמאה וערלה. Truma Tmeia VeOrla. So we discussed תרומה
טמאה Truma Tmeia is a unique category,
but anyway, and then it says the things that you normally bury
you bury, the things that you normally burn you burn. What does
that mean? It just said you burn it. So the גמרא Gemara
spells it out. הכיצד אוכלין בשריפה, HaKeitzad Ochlin BiSreifa, things that you
can burn you burn, like food. משקין, Mashkin, if it's liquid, not
oil, but liquids like wine or whatever, then בקבורה. BiKvurah. What do
you do? You can't burn them, you bury them. Although as I
told you actually when it comes to תרומה טמאה, Truma Tmeia, there's
a different הלכה Halacha that what do you call it? That you
are... that you actually use it as a type of an air
freshener. תרומה טמאה Truma Tmeia is different. It's not like classic איסורי
הנאה. Issurei Hana'ah. It's something that you're supposed to destroy and you
can be נהנה Neheneh from it in the process of destruction. Okay,
now actually the שיטה מקובצת Shita Mekubetzet says what?
It doesn't mean that you're חייב Chayav to do this air freshener
thing, just that you can.
Right, correct.
One minute. Okay. Okay, fine. So now the גמרא Gemara goes on.
חטאת העוף. Chatat HaOf. How
the חטאת העוף... Chatat HaOf... the שיטה מקובצת Shita Mekubetzet has a
whole other like few lines of the גמרא Gemara that are not
in our גמרא. Gemara. But anyway,
we'll skip it. Basically it says how we... if you're burning the
bread, how we... what's going to make sure that you're not going
to accidentally, you know, eat it as warm bread? It says okay,
you put it in a disgusting vessel so you make it disgusting
and then you use it for the firewood. Fine. Now the גמרא
Gemara goes on. חטאת העוף. Chatat HaOf. So now is the חטאת
העוף Chatat HaOf which is... the גמרא Gemara skips over the אשם
תלוי. Asham Talui. Remember that was the case where retroactively you found
out that it was... that it was חולין Chullin because it wasn't
necessary. So that was a whole discussion, a variation of the חולין
בעזרה Chullin BaAzara case where on the one hand it's not really
חייב שריפה, Chayav Sreifa, but because it looks like קדשים פסולים Kodshim
Psulim maybe you have to burn it or not. So we had
various debates. חטאת העוף Chatat HaOf even more looks like קדשים פסולים.
Kodshim Psulim. If I mean the אשם תלוי Asham Talui if retroactively
it was not necessary, so they were more inclined to say you
burn that. So those are things which are חולין Chullin which look
like קדשים. Kodshim. Then we get to the חטאת העוף Chatat HaOf
which is a ספק. Safek. You don't know whether it's a קרבן
Korban or not. You're allowed to bring it, you can't eat it,
you burn it. So let's take a look. תניא, Tanya, אמר רבי
יהודה, Amar Rebi Yehuda, חטאת
העוף הבאה על הספק, Chatat HaOf HaBa'ah Al HaSafek, this חטאת העוף
Chatat HaOf that you brought out of a doubt, so maybe it
is a קרבן Korban maybe it isn't. יטילנה לאמה, Yatilena LaAmah, you
throw it into the... this, you know,
channel, the water running through the בית המקדש. Beit HaMikdash. ומנתחה אבר
אבר, Umenatchah Eivar Eivar, you cut it up into limbs, presumably before
you throw it into the channel. וזורקה לאמה, Vezorkah LaAmah, and you
throw it into the channel. ומתגלגלת והולכת לנחל קדרון, Umitgalgelet VeHolechet LeNachal
Kidron, and because it's small and it dissolves or whatever, it goes
out in the channel. Now it's not exactly clear why here he
doesn't say burn it, because here actually it might be, it's not
like the other cases. The other cases you knew it wasn't a
קרבן. Korban. Here it might be a קרבן. Korban. But then maybe
that's exactly the problem. Since it's a קרבן, Korban, if it is
a קרבן, Korban, it's not a קרבן פסול, Korban Pasul, it's a
good חטאת העוף. Chatat HaOf. Then how are you allowed to actively
destroy something that's a קודש Kodesh קרבן? Korban? So maybe that's why
he says you have to be a little bit more passive about
it, that you throw it and you let it roll out and
so on. So therefore if it wasn't a קודש Kodesh קרבן Korban
you didn't have to burn it. If it was a קודש Kodesh
קרבן Korban at least you didn't actively destroy it.
Okay, you are cutting it into pieces.
Well you are, but that's not destroying. I mean that's chopping up
a chicken, you know, or not a chicken, a pigeon, whatever, you
know, cutting it up into, you know, its quarters. There is of
course another interesting possibility which is why don't you wait twenty-four hours
so that even if it were a קרבן Korban then it becomes
נותר Notar and then you burn
it? Anyway, those are... those are issues that come up in other
contexts. Okay, now we get to the basic principle. כל הנקברים לא
ישרפו. Kol HaNikbarim Lo Yisarefu. That you don't switch categories. You don't
burn things to be buried, buried things that are to be burned.
And let's take a look at the גמרא. Gemara. מאי טעמא? Mai
Ta'ama? Very important line of the גמרא. Gemara. משום דנקברין אפרן אסור.
Mishum DeNikbarin Afram Assur. Why do you not... meaning the מאי טעמא
Mai Ta'ama is not why don't you bury things that are to
be burned, although רש"י Rashi gave a reason, the best reason is
of course because there's a מצוה Mitzvah to burn that. But the
real question is why not burn things that need to be buried?
And we saw before that רבי יהודה Rebi Yehuda allows you to
be מחמיר. Machmir. So what's the reason not
to? משום דנקברין אפרן אסור. Mishum DeNikbarin Afram Assur. because things that
have to be buried, their ashes are forbidden, things that have to
be burnt, their ashes are permissible, and therefore if you burn something
that has to be buried, some would say oh ashes, it's got
to be מותר. muttar. You know, first of all, who would I
know where do the ashes came from? And if they came from
something אסור, assur, it was burnt, so the ashes are permissible. And
that's not true if there's no מצווה mitzvah to burn it. Now,
why is there this הלכה? halacha? The גמרא Gemara just says this,
you know, blank, a blanket statement. תוספות Tosafot actually has this line
in the משנה. Mishnah. It's clear from תוספות, Tosafot, but whether it
was in the משנה Mishnah or not, what's the reason for it?
Why, if basically if something is transformed and burnt, you would think
it's not the same thing? So you should be allowed to benefit
from it. What difference does it make if there's a מצווה mitzvah
to destroy it or not a מצווה mitzvah to destroy it?
How do you benefit from ashes?
Oh, well first of all you can use it as fertilizer. And
they would also use it for certain types of medical treatments, but
they would use it as fertilizer. It's like I think it is
just rich in nitrates and whatever. So there were ways to use
it. So what is the reason for this difference? So תוספות Tosafot
says a famous line in תוספות, Tosafot, maybe we'll look at it,
one line, if you take a
look back on ל"ג ע"ב, lamed gimmel amud bet, last תוספות, Tosafot,
הנשרפין אפרן מותר והנקברין אפרן אסור, hanisrafin afran muttar vehanikvarin afran assur,
צריך עיון טעמא מאי? tzarich iyun ta'ama mai? Why? If it's burnt
it should be okay, what difference does it make? ואמר מר דהנשרפין
כיון שצוה הכתוב ושרפן אחר שעשה כאילו נעשית מצותו. ve'omar mor dehanisrafin
keivan shetziva hakatuv veserafan achar she'asa keilu na'asit mitzvato. ואין דבר שנעשית
מצותו מועלין בו. ve'ein davar she'na'asit mitzvato mo'alin bo. So he compares
it to an ענין inyan of מעילה. me'ilah. We're not going to
worry about מעילה me'ilah right now, but he says if there's a
מצווה mitzvah to burn it and you've burnt it, then you've done
what needs to be
done. Meaning the way I would conceptualize this is the following: if
the Torah tells you here's how you're supposed to destroy it, then
after you've done the act, the Torah is basically saying okay, now
we consider it like it's destroyed. We told you burn it, that's
a מצווה mitzvah of how to destroy it, and now if you've
burnt it, we'll consider it destroyed, so whatever's left is not the
object, it's not the original object. Whereas if the Torah never told
you to burn it, to destroy it, the Torah just said don't
benefit from a שור הנסקל, shor haniskal, don't benefit from an עגלה
ערופה, eglah arufah, we're not telling you to destroy, we're just telling
you don't benefit. So therefore the Torah is never sort of acknowledging,
recognizing, calling what you did an act of destruction. You understand? So
therefore if the Torah says this is an act of destroying it,
it's implicitly saying what's left is not the object. But if you
on your own are trying to destroy it, the Torah never told
you anything, just that don't benefit, so maybe this is still some
remnant of the original object, halachically, although physically both cases are ashes,
but halachically in the first case it's considered to be the object
is gone, this is something new. In the case where there's no
מצווה mitzvah to destroy it, this is just some transformed version of
the previous thing, and therefore it remains forbidden in הנאה. hana'ah. Now
there is a general question, which is how much can something change
to be considered the thing itself? And like for example all the
discussions around gelatin, right, where you take these pig bones, so first
there's a question are bones really אסור assur if there's no meat
in them or whatever, but even so at a certain point where
you chemically process something, to what degree do you say that it
no longer is the original thing, it's something completely different, completely new?
So that's part of the question here. Even without the idea that
the Torah has a מצווה mitzvah to destroy it or not, you
might have thought that ashes are considered to be just physically completely
different type of a thing. So some say that it's only rabbinic,
the prohibition of the ashes afterwards, that it is true that biblically
it is a different thing. So some say it's only rabbinic. But
either way, the basic explanation here given is when there's a מצווה
mitzvah to destroy it, that means that it is considered to be
after you've done that מצווה, mitzvah, if there's an act of destroying
that the Torah demands, after that act is done, this thing is
considered to be done with. As if there's not a particular act
the Torah demands, then it's still, its status still remains.
So how much of it is left when you burn it? Do
you have to burn all of it, like you know, so every
part is ashes? Because once you've said once you've done the מצווה
mitzvah of שריפה sereifah it's מותר, muttar, so if I want I
can, not that I would do this, but you know, then you
can go through and eat a little piece of bagel that's...
No, no, the מצווה mitzvah שריפה sereifah is only done when you
get it to a point where it's no longer edible, where it's
no longer, like it has to be אינו ראוי לאכילת אדם, eino
ra'uy l'achilat adam, אינו ראוי לאכילת כלב, eino ra'uy l'achilat kelev, but
that's the מצווה mitzvah שריפה, sereifah, you're right, it's not so much
the act that constitutes lighting the fire and then you're done. Okay,
it has to be that the object has to be נשרף nisraf
as well.
So if there's still like little pieces of bagel there, then you
haven't fully done the שריפה.
sereifah. Exactly. Yeah. Okay, now let's take a look at the גמרא.
Gemara. Okay, so והנקברין אפרן אסור, vehanikvarin afran assur, is that really
true that everything that's buried the ashes are forbidden? והתניא תנא ברייתא,
vehatanya tana braita, דם הנדה ובשר המת, dam haniddah uvesar hamet,
the blood of a נדה niddah which is טמא tamei and that's
not אסור בהנאה, assur behana'ah, but the next case is the meat
of a corpse, the flesh of a corpse, that is טמא tamei
and a corpse is אסור בהנאה. assur behana'ah. So this is a
ברייתא braita about טומאה. tumah. It says although these things remain טמא
tamei even if they're dried up, but if they're dried to the
point שנפרכו, shenifrechu, that they are crumble when you touch them, they
are like so dried up that they crumble at the touch, טהורים.
tehorim. Then they no longer cause טומאה. tumah. So the גמרא Gemara
says מאי לאו טהורים ומותרין, mai lav tehorim umuttarin, does that not
mean that they're now considered not the object at all? so not
only are they טהור, tahor, the reason they're טהור tahor is they're
not considered the original object, and therefore they would also be מותר.
mutar. So that's similar to the idea that אפר afer is מותר,
mutar, and obviously there's no מצות שריפה mitzvas srefah of humans, right?
We bury, we don't cremate. So the גמרא Gemara says, לא טהורים
ואסורים. lo tehorim va-asurin. No, it's a law of טומאה. tumah. As
far as טומאה tumah is concerned, when it's that dried up, it's
no longer טמא, tamei, but it's still as far as הנאה hana'ah
is concerned, it's still considered the original object and still אסור בהנאה.
asur be-hana'ah. מתיב רב פנחס, Masiv Rav Pinchas, רב פנחס Rav Pinchas
asks, עולת העוף שנתמצה דמה. olat ha-of she-nitmatzta dama. So if you
take this bird sacrifice and you squeeze out the blood, right, which
is what you do by these bird עולות, olot, מוראתה ונוצתה יצאו
מידי מעילה. murtah ve-notzah yatzu midei me'ilah. Then the crop and the
feathers, where the תורה Torah says you basically leave them by the
side of the מזבח, mizbe'ach, whatever, those things there's no longer prohibition
of מעילה me'ilah because the מצוה mitzvah is now done with this
קרבן. korban. מאי לאו יצאו מידי מעילה ומותרים? mai lav yatzu midei
me'ilah u-mutarin? Doesn't that mean that they're no longer מעילה me'ilah and
now these things are actually permissible? Now that's actually quite interesting because
that wasn't even a case of similar to שריפה sref at all,
so exactly what the comparison was was not clear. But anyway, the
גמרא Gemara says, לא יצאו מידי מעילה ואסורים. lo yatzu midei me'ilah
va-asurin. No, just because there's no מעילה me'ilah does not mean that
they're permissible in benefit. They can still remain forbidden in benefit. Okay,
but if you do benefit, you haven't transgressed מעילה. me'ilah. You haven't
transgressed מעילה, me'ilah, right. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara seems to feel
that there were tried to ask some questions, that there were contradiction,
but says no, it's not true. These things do remain forbidden in
הנאה. hana'ah. So now the גמרא Gemara goes on to ask the
other angle. ונסרפין דהקדש אפרן מותר? ve-nisrafin de-hekdesh afran mutar? So first
we tried to prove that there are cases where the אפר afer
is not forbidden, and we said no, if it's נשרפין, nisrafin, the
אפר afer remains forbidden. Now we're asking from the other angle. Is
it really true that when there's a מצוה mitzvah to be שורף
soref it, the אפר afer becomes permissible? והתניא, ve-hatanya, we taught in
a ברייתא, Braitah, כל הנשרפין אפרן מותר. kol ha-nisrafin afran mutar. Every,
all the things that are burned, their ashes are permissible. That's our
principle. But then there's an exception. חוץ מאפר אשירה ואפר דהקדש לעולם
אסור. chutz me-efer asherah ve-efer de-hekdesh le-olam asur. The אפר afer of
an אשירה asherah and the אפר afer of הקדש. hekdesh. And our
משנה Mishnah spoke about הקדש hekdesh cases that you have to burn.
And here the ברייתא Braitah says that when you burn הקדש, hekdesh,
the ashes remain forbidden. So what is it? When you burn הקדש,
hekdesh, are the ashes permissible or do they remain forbidden? So the
גמרא Gemara says, ומערבינהו ולא קערבינהו. u-m'arvinhu ve-lo ka-arvinhu. Now the first
question is, why didn't it just say it as one sentence? חוץ
מאפר אשירה והקדש. chutz me-efer asherah ve-hekdesh. Why did it separate as
two statements?
You know, חוץ מאפר אשירה ואפר הקדש.
chutz
me-efer asherah ve-efer hekdesh.
So this is just a parenthetical point.
ותני להו, ve-tani lehu, why didn't it just say them as one
phrase, אפר אשירה והקדש? efer asherah ve-hekdesh? Why did it say separate
statements? משום דאשירה יש לה בטילה בבני כוכבים הקדש אין לו בטילה
עולמית. mishum de-asherah yesh lah bitulah be-vnei kochavim hekdesh ein lo bitulah
olamit. Because there are different הלכות. halachot. That if you have an
אשירה, asherah, a tree that was worshipped, that actually there are ways
it could become permissible. How does it become permissible? If the non-Jews
who worshipped it nullify its status as עבודה זרה. avodah zarah. But
הקדש hekdesh that became פסול pasul can never become permissible. So because
there are differences, we do not just lump them into one category.
Fine, that was a parenthetical point. קתני מיהת, katani mihat, we taught
nevertheless, אפר הקדש לעולם אסור, efer hekdesh le-olam asur, that the אפר
afer of הקדש hekdesh is אסור. asur. And our משנה Mishnah says
the אפר afer of הקדש hekdesh is מותר, mutar, because one of
the cases of our משנה Mishnah was הקדש. hekdesh. So אמר רמי
בר חמא, amar Rami bar Chama, כגון דנפלה דליקה בהיכלי הקדש מאליה.
kegon de-nafla deleika be-heichalei hekdesh me-eleha. Ah, why is it that their
ashes are permissible? Because of this, again, this is really where you
have to introduce תוספות, Tosafot, because of נעשית מצותו. na'asis mitzvato. You
did the מצוה mitzvah act. So what if they got burned by
accident? What if a fire broke out? So although they are burned,
since you did not do the act of destroying, the תורה Torah
is only willing to say it's considered destroyed if you did the
מצוה mitzvah of destroying it. You did it. If there was an
act of destruction done. If they happened to be burned, then it
goes back to the normal principle that we'll consider ashes to be
the same thing until you've done the מצוה mitzvah of destruction. So
in that cases, כיון דלא ידי מאן דלא הוי אינש דלימא דלא
יפיק אפרן לחולין. kivan de-lo yadi man de-lo havei inish de-lima de-lo
yafik afran le-chulin. Now this is a funny phrase because it starts
intertwining מעילה, me'ilah,
so the גר"א Gra cut out some of these words, but we'll
read them. Since nobody knew about it, there was no מעילה, me'ilah,
and if there was no מעילה, me'ilah, it did not become חולין.
chulin. Okay, but the point is fine, but besides the fact that
through מעילה me'ilah it becomes חולין, chulin, you know, there's still just
the other question about the fact that you burned it should have
made it מותר. mutar. So really the point is, right, there's two
ways in which הקדש hekdesh could become מותר. mutar. One is if
you do מעילה, me'ilah, it becomes חולין. chulin. And the other is
if you do the מצוה mitzvah of destroying it. Forget חולין, chulin,
because you've done the מצוה mitzvah of destroying it, of burning it,
it became מותר. mutar. So here it's sort of saying both points.
It happened by itself, there was no מעילה, me'ilah, that won't get
you off the hook. But the more relevant point is, since you
did not do the מצוה mitzvah of שריפה, srefah, although they were
burned, without you having done the מצוה, mitzvah, it does not become
מותר. mutar. So that's why, that's the case where it's forbidden is
a special case where you did not do the מצוה mitzvah of
burning it. רב שמעיה אמר, Rav Shemaya amar, כי תניא ההיא בתרומת
הדשן תניא. ki tanya ha-hi be-trumat ha-deshen tanya. When does it say
that the אפר afer is forbidden? It's a very special case. Normal
things like טמא, tamei, פיגול, pigul, נותר, notar, those things you burn.
burn it and their ashes are permissible. There's a מצוה *mitzvah* to
burn. If you were to say the ashes are forbidden is a
very particular ash. Not something you burn by itself? Not something, right,
well, no, that would probably not cause that case. Not something that
became פסול *pasul* that there was a מצוה *mitzvah* to burn, normal
case of ashes. What's normal ashes in the בית המקדש *Beit HaMikdash*?
Something about the ashes from on top of the מזבח *mizbe'ach*. So
the, and every morning you take off those ashes, you do a
תרומת הדשן *trumat hadeshen*, you put them by the side of the
ramp, right? So there, בתרומת הדשן תניא דלעולם אסור *bitrumat hadeshen tanya
d'le'olam assur*, the ashes of the morning removal of ashes, that is
forbidden. Not that there's איסורי הנאה *issurei hana'ah* and a מצוה *mitzvah*
to destroy it, and that's the issue with those things, like if
you burn נותר *notar* or טמא *tamei*, the ashes are permissible. Here
there's a separate הלכה *halacha* of תרומת הדשן *trumat hadeshen*, שנתניא ושמו
*she'tanya v'samo*, you shall place it, the תרומת הדשן *trumat hadeshen*, בנחת
*benachat*, like pleasantly, don't throw it down. ושמו כולו *v'samo kulo*, place
all of it by the side. ושמו שלא יפזר *v'samo shelo yefazer*,
that it shouldn't scatter. Now of course it's not clear exactly, but
the implicit point here is you leave it there also, okay, that
you don't remove it, and from there we learn that the ashes
of the תרומת הדשן *trumat hadeshen* are אסור בהנאה *assur behana'ah*. So
it's saying it's completely categorically different. If you have something that became
פסול *pasul* as a קרבן *korban* and you burn it and there's
a מצות שריפה *mitzvah sreifah*, like נותר *notar*, טמא *tamei*, פיגול *pigul*,
then the ashes are מותר *mutar*. When there's a מצות שריפה *mitzvah
sreifah*, the ashes are מותר *mutar*. Here there's a special הלכה *halacha*,
ashes of תרומת הדשן *trumat hadeshen*, there's a מצוה *mitzvah* to place
them down and not to benefit from them, and there there's a
special דין *din* that the ashes of תרומת הדשן *trumat hadeshen* are
אסור *assur*. What was not discussed is why are the ashes of
an עבודה זרה *avodah zarah*, of an אשרה *asheirah*, אסור *assur*? Whatever
happened to the principle that if there's a מצוה *mitzvah* to destroy
it and you've destroyed it, it's permissible? So one of the אחרונים
*acharonim* says an answer, it's not so clear what he's getting at.
One of the אחרונים *acharonim* says because by עבודה זרה *avodah zarah*
we have a special הלכה *halacha* that חליפי עבודה זרה אסור *chalifei
avodah zarah assur*. If I sell James my idol and he pays
me money for it, the איסור הנאה *issur hana'ah* transfers, it's not
only on the idol, but it also, not transfers, extends, like תמורה
*tmurah*, sort of like תמורה *tmurah*, it remains on the object and
it extends, it also goes on the money. So by עבודה זרה
*avodah zarah* you have a concept that even if it's not the
original object, if it's somehow derived from the object like money paid,
therefore the prohibition also goes on that. So ashes, even if we
say they're not the object, they're no worse than having paid money,
they derived from the object and therefore they remain אסור *assur*. So
that's what one of the אחרונים *acharonim* said, very nice explanation. But
again, the upshot is if there's a מצוה *mitzvah* to destroy it
and you burn it, after it's burnt, it's considered a different thing.
If there's not a מצוה *mitzvah* to destroy it, then even when
it changes form, it remains forbidden בהנאה *behana'ah*, and that's the reason
that נתבערו עפרן אסור *nitba'aran afran assur*. הדרן עלך קדשי מזבח וסליקא
לה מסכת תמורה *Hadran alach kodshei mizbe'ach u'selika lah masechet tmurah*. Wow,
good thing that was only an עמוד *amud*, because that took us
a lot longer than I thought.